[Music]
we will
discuss in this um last lecture several
applications of what we have been doing
in particular of pank Hope
tomorrow I'll give you an overview and
the review of the whole subject and then
I'll give you a show
also first about rotations in
space what does a rotation mean well
think of it this way simply a rigid body
like this it's terribly heavy and then
you just put it in some other
position okay without you moving the
center of
gravity so from this to this that's
rotation you might think of rotation as
the following operation you fix some
axis for example vertical axis and you
do this but it doesn't have to be that
way rotation simply means take a rigid
body put it in another position but
without moving the center of gravity is
that
okay now it is true that every rotation
as we have just defined fixes an axis
that is if you apply a rotation there's
an entire line passing through the
origin that does not
move but that's not obvious for example
if I rotate this thing around the
vertical axis it's like that and if I
rotate it along the horizontal axis like
this it's like this okay so from this
position it came to this position is it
clear that there was an axis around
which I rotated well it turns out that
there's an axis like that somewhere in
between around which I can rotate but it
is more of a theorem than an Evidence so
I shall Begin by discussing the first
application which is very
[Applause]
easy application
22 if
rotation in R3 and more generally all
dimensional Vector space and ukan
space fixes some
axis yeah so this is a whole
line
now let's remark in case you think that
this
is obvious that rotation looks like this
and you are spinning an object around
something
that this statement is
false in even Nal
space for
example let's take the simplest don't
trial even Dimension space that's
R2 and the usual thing let's take the
rotation of this
which you know spins the whole thing
around and
around like that
okay there is something that is
fixed and that is the
origin yes but everything else in the
plane is moved by the rotation
everything moves so the this origin is
not an axis axis means a whole line a
onedimensional subset is left fixed so
it's not true in dimension two a
rotation fixes only one
point okay similarly in all even
Dimensions hi good morning um all even
Dimensions rotations don't necessarily
fix anything only the center of gravity
of the object but in all dimensional
spaces rotation always fixes an entire
onedimensional
Subspace that's quite remarkable
now various proofs of this fact exist
and one of them is essentially linear
algebra but
um our
proof is simply as follows if you have
such a rotation imagine rotating
okay let's look at this rotation but do
it in slow
motion when you do it in slow motion it
induces a vector
field if you like the derivative of this
rotation on the sphere which is inside
the space that is on an even dimensional
sphere s even which is in fact s odd
minus one which is
inside our odd in question so one
dimension
fewer
okay and so we have a vector field a
dynamical system on this sphere but we
saw that when you have a dynamical
system on a sphere in fact on any
manifold the behavior of that dynamical
system is constrained by the topology of
the manifold so um in this
case
um by the theorem 19 that we proved
yesterday that
is the oil characteristic of this thing
gives you a minimum number of fixed
points that this Vector field must
have the vector field we have must have
at
least how many fixed
points what's the order characteristic
of s
even two early in the morning and
two fix
points okay so
two let's say here and say
here but you see if those two fix points
are fixed then the entire axis that
connects those two fix two points must
be fixed as well because it's a rotation
it's a ukle
motion and then the axis joining
[Applause]
them is also
fixed okay so you can see that in all
dimensional spaces a whole axis fixed by
every rotation it's not true as I
emphasized in even dimensional spaces
that's our first
application
okay second
um let's um discuss another field of
mathematics or mathematical Sciences um
computer
Graphics now we are not going to of
course discuss in any detail any of the
aspects mathematical aspects of computer
Graphics but there's an interesting
operation um that would be useful in
such a field which is
this let's ask can we
design a continuous algorithm I hope the
intuitive meaning is will become clear
Contin algorithm let's call it a such
that it
[Applause]
assigns to each
Vector in
R3 bless you a
nonzero
um Vector which we shall call a u also
in R3 which is perpendicular to
U what I mean is you know you have a
vector like this and then there's an
algorithm from that computes from this
Vector a vector which is perpendicular
to this and if you're given a vector
like this there's an algorithm that
computes a perpendicular Vector like
this and if once again you have a vector
like this perhaps this algorithm is
going to compute a vector like this and
so on so on well in R2 as you can see
it's perfectly possible and extremely
easy you just rotate the whole thing by
90° but in R3 if you think about
it there's an ambiguity let's say that
this is the vector we're given and you
say rotate it by 90° well 90° in which
direction this way this way this way
this way this way this way this way I
mean there is a huge amount of ambiguity
you might say well rotate it in any
direction ah but that's not an algorithm
algorithm means that the computer must
be told exactly in which direction to
rot
moreover that direction that algorithm
must be continuous which means that if I
take a slightly different Vector the
result must be slightly different from
the original vector and so on is the
position of the problem clear okay and
such a
thing such an
algorithm would be
useful in computer Graphics it turns out
computer
Graphics in R3
okay for example it would be useful in
many
[Applause]
areas what do you think
can we design such an
algorithm the
answer is no you cannot design such an
algorithm continuous
algorithm because you
see if yes for contradiction then
the vector field a of U which where U
belongs to
S2 would be a continuous Vector
field every a nonzero Vector
field on what is the unit sphere inside
R3 on S2 which is exactly this
yeah in other words on this two you
would have at this point look at the
radius vector and I know that there is a
well as hyp there's a vector which is
perpendicular to it but this Vector then
is tangent to the sphere similarly to
such a radius Vector you might have a
vector which is like this so you should
be able to define a nonzero every un
nonzero Vector field all over the sphere
but that there such a thing
exist no it doesn't
[Applause]
exist contradicting the same
Theory because every Vector field on S2
on any manifold of nonzero order
characteristic you must have fixed
points in other words you must have
zeros of the vector
field okay that's quite good you might
also like to
um look at the remark 20 which
immediately
follows okay that was my second suggest
for application many other
applications let's
do a third application which
is a bit of a joke um we shall consider
a very very theoretical meteorology do
you know what meteorology means it means
they study science of weather yeah Sunny
rainy snowy which doesn't per happen and
so
on in French you say Meto for the
English weather forecast yeah
very theal meteorology
um think of the wind that blows Cape
Town is famous for the wind the strong
gust wind which is blowing from
Southeast and so
on and you ask yourself well here it's
probably a windy day it's blowing and
perhaps in Egypt along the Nile the wind
is is blowing in Russia across the
Siberian plane the wind is blowing and
maybe in Brazil the wind is blowing
along the beach and so on and on the in
the middle of the ocean and wind is
blowing and so
on can it happen that all over the
surface of the Earth the wind is
blowing you know if the surface of the
Earth were not as we know it but say
topologically the Taurus as we saw it's
easy to make the wind blow everywhere
right if one day you
have the wind pattern like this then it
will
be the case that the on the everywhere
on this Taurus the wind wind is blowing
right on the surface of the Earth can it
happen that wind is blowing everywhere
the answer is no because the surface of
the Earth
you see ideally in mathematical
idealization is essentially a two
dimensional sphere so this very
theoretical metodology says that
at any
moment there must be a lull lol l l l in
English means a point where there's no
wind or state of
knowing there must exist some point
on the surface of the
Earth and we shall assume that this
is homeomorphic test two in fact it's
not quite hom to anyway
um
where the
wind is not
blowing where there is no wind excuse me
the existence with
low this statement is of course as I say
a bit of a joke but it's Anyway by no
means obvious so depending on the
nature the topology of the
surface sometimes you can easily
construct an everywhere a non zero wind
field if you like but not on the surface
of the Earth
so there are some problems with saying
that the surface of the Earth is S2 but
okay please forgive us um excuse me why
is that a problem H why is that a
problem well because you see the when we
say the wind we are always tacitly
thinking horizontal wind but you might
because the atmosphere has finite
thickness you can have wind going up and
down and then you see if you have a wind
field which is like this this you can
say oh here there is wind because the
air current is going up or coming down
but that means that you are no longer
doing topology on the
surface on the two dimensional surface
we are saying that if you have a vector
field that's everywhere tangent to say
S2 that Vector field must have an
equilibrium or zero must vanish
somewhere but in fact the atmosphere is
not two dimensional S2 so
there's a problem but let's say that
it's
okay the next application
is very
interesting or I hope it will interest
many of us but it is somewhat um it
requires a little bit of knowledge so if
you don't have any clue what I'm talking
about please just relax and sit back but
I'll try to explain what we do it's an
application to general
relativity we are now discussing then
yet another field of science okay you
see what the wide range of applications
topology can have if only you exercise
imagination and flexibility of mind so
generativity as you know very famous
Theory and you have probably heard of
something called black
holes in popular literature black hole
is usually presented as a something very
very massive very heavy stuff which has
collapsed to perhaps a small region and
which is so dense that it attracts
everything from around the surrounding
space and nothing can escape this
gravitational field and so on that's
probably the image of black hole that we
have well in the actual mathematical for
comination of
generativity that's of course the
physical picture we should have but you
can say it in another way it turns out
that in gener activity what you do is
this SpaceTime We Have A Spacetime which
is a manifold of Dimension
four and on this manifold you define
what is called a metric in other words a
way of measuring if you like distance
angle and so on however unlike in
standard you could be or ranian geometry
this metric has a very peculiar feature
you know when you discuss dot products
of two vectors A1 B1 C1 dot A2 B2
C2 and in three dimensional space you
multiply the components and add them
yes in that's the standard geometry and
we say that this me is positive definite
because if you calculate the square of
any Vector you get something positive
well of course you say however in
relativity for a
certain interesting reason you don't use
a positive definite metric if you take
the dot product of two vectors and now
each Vector has four
components the first three components
which represent space
they are multiplied together and added
A1 A2 plus B1 B2 plus C1
C2 but the last component which
represents time are
multiplied but subtract subtract it
minus and it turns out this is very
important in order to in order to
guarantee that the speed of light in
vacuum is everywhere the same it turns
out interesting any way so in relativity
you use this funny metric funny if you
like dot to Scala product okay and
that's called indefinite signature
metric and more specifically lorenzian
metric okay this is called
Laurentian and in contrast this is
called
rmania okay and
moreover in lenan case you can have
coefficients in front that vary from
space to space point to point so the
metric becomes a function of time a
function of point on the manifold and
that dependence on where you are in
space time you know the metric might
look different here from what it looks
here and so on is the mathematical
formulation of the fact that the space
is curved that's what it means for the
space to be curved that metric is not
constant
okay so in gener activity um we have
have a lenan
metric usually noted by G any Matrix is
usually denoted by G and so this is a
4x4 um symmetric
Matrix yeah that varies
um of signature or important thing is
signature not plus but plus plus plus
minus and that
depends that varies let's
say smoothly or
continuously from point to
point in some textbook treatments the
signature is not plus plus plus minus
but plus minus- minus it doesn't matter
which one you use this one is slightly
more pleasant geometrically because you
can think of the threedimensional
standard ranium manifold as a subset of
this by just looking at the first three
components and say uh but when we add
time you get the negative Direction but
it doesn't matter which signature you
use we are going to use that signature
okay and which is
defined on a four dimensional
manifold
over four
dimensional
manifold and let's call it
m
called space
time that's the mathematical setup in an
now the claim is as
follows this
metric I said that the coefficients can
be fun functions in fact are usually
functions because the space is curved
and those functions are continuous
functions smooth functions however
sometimes you it might happen that some
of those coefficients blow up in other
words become Infinity well you don't
want to have sitations like that right
or sometimes that those coefficients
become um so degenerate that this metric
becomes degenerate so it becomes zero
well you don't want to have situations
like that either it should be um
signature and non degenerate Matrix but
some things can happen those um
catastrophes if you like are called
singularities and that is the
mathematical picture of what a black
hole is singularities in the
metric okay just as the metric depend
varying from point to point
mathematically represents the curvedness
of the space so the singularity is
something bad happening to this metric
is exactly what black holes are well
when I say exactly I mean you should
think of black holes that way it's not
quite exactly what black holes out but
anyway the claim then is as follows you
cannot avoid
singularities in some
contexts
okay suppose for example that
the oil characteristic of your
SpaceTime is not zero
then for example what's a good example
suppose that your manold is
topologically S4 so maybe one in one
model cosmology the space time is a four
dimensional sphere who
knows in this case an even dimensional
sphere has already a characteristic too
so you would certainly be non zero okay
in such a
case then G must
must become
singular
s and you can Loosely I said exactly but
I take it back but Loosely think of
these as black
holes something goes
wrong with the metric interesting huh so
just from the topological hypothesis on
the space time you can sometimes deduce
that the metric cannot be regular
everywhere of course for other choices
of this SpaceTime model you might be
able to define the lorenzian smooth or
metric everywhere but not always not on
all manifolds not on all
models here is the proof which I shall
write over there
let's argue by contradiction suppose
that g has no
Singularity then you can draw the
following picture at each point in space
time at this point in space time there
is a direction which we shall call space
Direction and although I'm drawing
something that looks like 2D this is a
threedimensional space okay I cannot
draw that picture so I'm going to
represent the threedimensional uh
spatial Direction by a plane and then
there is a direction which is the time
Direction yeah and
that's 1D one
dimensional space time and you might
know that the light propagates at
constant speed in vacuum everywhere so
there is what is called a light
com what this means is that
any existence any world line must fit
inside this light con because if I have
a curve which is going outside this
light con which that means that for the
some unit of time I have traveled faster
than what this 45° angle represents
which is a speed of light you cannot
exceed the speed of light anywhere
so at least in vacuum so that's the
light com okay so at each
point there exists some sort of object
like this which is called light con okay
now it turns out that once you have a
light con so please imagine that this is
a threedimensional Direction but there's
one dimensional Direction at long time
it turns out to be easy to average over
the right and Define the average
direction of time what I mean is well
well the you know time axis might be
pointing this way pointing this way
pointing this way but you can average
over that's actually a very easy
operation so in this
scenario this part of the light con
corresponds to the
Future this part corresponds to the
past and that's the present that's where
you are that's when you are okay and all
the events in the past might propagate
and reach you so those are the
influences but if something happened in
the past but very very far away then it
still hasn't had time to reach you
because it can propagate at most at the
speed of light so it hasn't affected you
for example if the sun our sun explodes
at this very moment we will not know
that anything happened for about 8
minutes because the sun is eight light
minutes
away there is no way that the explosion
of the Sun will affect us it's not true
that as soon as the sun explodes we get
like this because even that kind of
shock wave cannot travel faster than the
speed of light no information travels
faster than speed of light not even the
information that are the there's a star
exploding okay so there is a finite
limit to the speed at which information
propagates therefore the only inference
on you that can come that can affect you
is here and the only events that you can
affect in the future are here and so on
but anyway that's future and past right
so if G has no Singularity let's go back
then as I have just drawn at every point
on the manifold we can
draw this um space time diag this
lighton
diagram and in particular we can
draw a vector
tangent to the space time so
[Applause]
that
um V of X non
zero points or is directed along the
average future Direction
[Applause]
okay here you might want to imagine
something you know I don't know which
way may be like this
VX and you can do this in a continuous
fashion from point to point
um okay
but
um theorem 19 again which says that the
number of fixed points or number of
equilibria of a vector field on a
manifold is bounded below by the order
characteristic and if the Order
character is non zero that means that
there must be an equilibrium so by
theorem 19
forces V to be zero somewhere
on M which contradicts that
[Applause]
statement
proof
okay thus we have even an application of
topology to general relativity to
cosmological questions it is a baby
application but there are many deeper
and and more exciting applications to
all areas of
physics okay any questions about those
one two three four applications that we
have discussed of
p
no in that
case this is the end of chapter 5 and it
is the end of the main material that I
wanted to present to you and share with
you in this
course I'd like to conclude them the
main part of the course of the lecture
course by giving you a little
appendix you know when you go have a
dinner at a and elsewhere it's nice if
there's a dessert after the meal so this
is something like a
dessert an appendix will deserve
[Applause]
you have all heard of the fundamental
theorem of
algebra yes that a polinomial with
complex coefficients for example must
have a root somewhere provided you are
looking for a root among the complex
numbers yeah you may not have a real
root but it always has a complex root
and once you know that it's very easy to
prove that in fact by UK an algorithm
and so on if the polinomial has degree D
then they are D Roots some of these
roots might be multiple but anyway D
Roots When you count the multiplicities
properly you all know
this does everyone know how to prove
it you might have seen a proof there are
many different ways of proving it and
the most standard proof nowadays in an
undergraduate curriculum uses complex
analysis something called L's theorem
very nice argument which says that a
holomorphic function which is bounded
everywhere on the complex plane must be
constant but anyway so there are many
proofs but I'd like to give you a
topological proof of the fundamental
theorem algebra